The meditation techniques popular today
are not what the Buddha taught as
mindfulness. But the sutras do talk
about the four foundations of
mindfulness, mindfulness of the body and
so on. How should those practices be
understood? What is their true purpose
and at which stage do they come into
play? If you look at the sutras
themselves, um when the Buddha talked about
um when the Buddha talked about
satipana,
uh they were taught to monks and it
clearly states there after they would
have already been practicing the gradual
training thoroughly. So even like the
newly ordained monks would have been
would have given up um sensuality,
sexuality, eating at the wrong time, association,
eating at the wrong time, association,
crowd with people, family, they would
have given all of that up. And then the
Buddha taught them the recollections of
um
the four foundations of recollection
basically. And numerous sutras in um I
think Satipatanut in Majimanikai as well
um even add that basically after the
monk is thoroughly established in virtue
upon virtue uh on the basis of virtue he
practices these
how it's called. So, it's important
because it's not basically it's not a um
it's not a technique. It's not a method
that anybody can just pick up
regardless of where their mind minds are
at. Um so you realize that the whole
training already begins through as we
said often training in virtue and so on.
So satipatana the four foundations of
recollections would be just like a say a
more unified form of training in that
virtue in that restraint that you would
have already been training in and then
on top of that when the Buddha taught
anapanasati that was taught to people
who were at least sautanas
in the suta. So um as a as a form of
satipatana anapanasati was even a more
say specific way of development there
was pretty much for those that already
had the right viewati
suta clearly states that so again the
problem is not in you trying to do it
trying to understand what these
practices are the problem is taking them
um well the problem is thinking that
whatever idea you get about that
practice is while being a non-stop while
being somebody who is not still
established in virtue and gradual
training and withdrawal from sensuality
you think that idea is right you think
that's what anapanati is you think
that's what satipan is and then through
merely adhering to doing it mechanically
you will get where you need to be
and that's what the problem is
basically it doesn't apply to you which
means you're not in a position to
understand it until the prerequis
requisites are met both satipana anapana
suta it's not a meditation it's
certainly not a concentration practice
it's a practice of nonforgetfulness
literally the name sati says that memory
not forgetting not forgetting the four
reference points whether you sitting
walking talking
not forgetting it because that means
you're not forgetting the context of
your situation
by not forgetting the context of your
situation well it's a lot harder to
become I'm careless. It's a lot harder
to make wrong choices, choices rooted in
greed, aversion, distraction. That's why
virtue establishment in virtue basically
nearly like like practicing towards
sotapati and then becoming a sautana is
necessary for anapanosati because in
order to um rightly
recognize the the the choice of aversion
or non-avversion uh lust and non-lust
you would have need had to properly
train in virtue for a sufficient amount
of time i.e not choosing lust aversion
and distraction as a default. So that's
why it's like it's not a negotiable
basis. It's not like oh let me do this
technique and then my virtue will
develop as a result of it. No satipana
is already the result of virtue result
of the training.
Furthermore the the reference point of
chitta the the third satipatana again
sautapana is the one that sees his
chitta. Nobody shorter than sautapana
sees their chitta.
So there is nothing to apply to you
there because you don't have the
necessary requirements
rather than falling into a trap of yeah
but you know everybody says the the
entire terra says it says like yeah but
what is that based on it's based on
Buddha ghost's commentary and study
monks from 10 centuries 15 centuries ago
whenever he was there was like 6,000 of
them living at at at at at the monastery
and just just writing papers and
translating uh pali and and recording
stuff. So not exactly a reference point
for somebody who practices in seclusion
uh diligently in remote dwellings for
the dispassion and and uprooting of all
the killesa. So the point is like re
restrain your tendency to to just accept
that idea of like shortcut and start
training in that which you can actually
train. Precepts
Precepts
taming of the senses that will reveal
the signs and the characteristics of
that animal that will make it more
apparent. That will make its nature more
obvious to you. That will make you
basically realize that you can't own it
even if you want to. Then it becomes a
reference point like your body. That's
what Satipatana Suta says.
He knows mind affected with lust as mind
affected lust. Actually as in actually
he directly sees the wild animal
agitated with lust. Right there like
like you would look at the the animal a
lustful animal or or or excited animal
or disturbed animal in front of you.
You' say, "Okay, that's a problem.
because it could cause me harm. It could
make me sort of, you know, it will make
me pay the price but it's not my problem
in that direct sense. It's not me who is
affected by this. I see it clearly where
it is so I don't lose the sight of it so
that I don't pay the price.
And you could see like if you're
practicing such right nonforgetfulness
of the state of the animal, whatever
that state of the animal is,
aren't will be the the only possible
outcome of that.
But that means at any given point you
know where the animal is and what it is
doing, what state it is in, what
feelings it is in, what intentions are
evolving around it
and in and of itself paired with the v
paired with the virtue that would have
revealed the animal paired with the
right choices that would have outlined
the whole satipatana practice as in the
four foundations that are there whether
to take them or not. They basically
exist. You contemplating them rightly in
a sense of not not concentrating on them
as an object of your attention but not
completely forgetting about them either.
Letting them be on the peripheral,
letting them basically become a backdrop
of your day-to-day choices. That is how
you separate yourself from the whole
thing. That's how you disown it because
you see you see damas coming and going.
You see chitta changing, you see
feelings coming and going, you see body
being subjected to everything else. So
there will be no layer left for you to
entertain any sense of ownership if the
practice of satipana is successfully
developed.